A Guide to the Papers of Paul Spivey ca. 1881-1967, n.d.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Paul Spivey 1881-1967, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6560-e
The papers of Paul Spivey consist of ca. 2,500 items (7 Hollinger boxes, 2 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Mrs. Helen Spivey O'Neal (daughter of Paul Spivey), of Norfolk, Virginia, on March 6, 1991.
Biographical/Historical Information
Mr. and Mrs. Davis lived at their Morven Park estate, near Leesburg, Loudoun County, Virginia, where they raised purebred cattle. Davis was governor of Virginia from 1918-1922; he had studied law at the University of Virginia, but graduated from Columbia University, New York, and practiced law in New York City. At forty-four, Davis moved to Virginia and became editor of The Southern Planter.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Paul Spivey consist of ca. 2500 items (7 Hollinger boxes, 2 linear feet), ca. 1881-1967, and undated, chiefly papers generated in his capacity as co-executor of the estate of Marguerite G. (Inman) Davis (186[7?]-1963) and by his assistance to Mrs. Davis in settling the estate of her husband, Governor Westmoreland Davis (1859-1942).
This collection includes estate papers, correspondence, legal and business documents, plats, photographs, and printed material. Also included is material concerning Spivey's position as business manager and editor of The Southern Planter(established in 1840) and later as the president and publisher of the magazine, following Westmoreland Davis's death in 1942. Davis became the president and publisher of The Southern Planter in 1912, and Spivey went to work for Davis in 1915 as his business manager.
The first series (Boxes 1-2) of this collection consists of the correspondence of Westmoreland and Marguerite Davis and Paul Spivey. The correspondence of Westmoreland Davis and Paul Spivey is almost totally about the running of The Southern Planter business, including the financial affairs of the paper, editorials, exhibits, topics to discuss in the paper, costs of supplies used for the paper, and possible changes to the printing press (1926 Jan 2[6?]), but other financial affairs of the Davis's are also discussed. For very similar material concerning the magazine see The Southern Planter folder in the second series.
The correspondence of Paul Spivey and Marguerite Davis dates from the death of Westmoreland Davis in 1942 when Spivey assisted Mrs. Davis in settling the estate of her husband. Spivey continued to manage and administer the financial affairs of Mrs. Davis in conjunction with the representatives of the United States Trust Company of New York until her death in 1963.
These letters chiefly discuss the repairs and upkeep of Morven Park, and the negotiations to eventually give Morven Park to Washington and Lee University (1951 Mar 14 & 30 and April 20 & 27), Mrs. Davis's federal taxes, the Inman Properties in New York, the Florida Trading Company (see folder in second series), the sale of Morven Park acreage, the daily financial concerns of Mrs. Davis, and the Westmoreland Davis Memorial Foundation (see folder in second series) set up by Mrs. Davis to perpetuate and honor the memory of Governor Davis and his service to Virginia.
Spivey was an officer of the Westmoreland Davis Memorial Foundation (Vice-President); when Mrs. Davis expressed her wishes to Mr. Diefenbach of the United States Trust Company of New York, he would consult with Spivey concerning Virginia charities. Also present among the letters of Mrs. Davis and Paul Spivey are letters from Alice Profitt, the companion of Mrs. Davis in her later years, about Mrs. Davis's health and affairs.
Many of the subjects discussed in the correspondence files also have additional related material in the second series. The folders for the entire collection are in reverse chronological order and have maintained the original folder headings whenever they could be ascertained.
The second series consists of the financial and legal papers of the Davis family, with some material dating back to the financial affairs of various members of the Inman family of Mrs. Davis. A large portion of this material pertains to the settling of the estates of Westmoreland and Marguerite Davis, their estate tax returns, and the law firms of Carter, Ledyard & Milburn of New York and Stirling Harrison, Leesburg, Virginia, involved in the settlement.
Other files pertaining to the Davis' financial interests include audits for Morven farms and the Loudoun Times Publishing Company; the Central Manhattan Improvement Company; the Federal Land Bank of Baltimore; the Florida Trading Corporation; the Hotel Chelsea in New York; the house at King and Cornwall Streets, Leesburg, Virginia; the Loudoun Times-Mirror; and The Southern Planter.
Political papers of Westmoreland Davis include folders concerning the Federal Reserve Bank Directors; the Market Commission Bill & Bureau of Markets; political papers, chiefly concerning the gubernatorial primary of 1917 involving J. Taylor Ellyson, John Garland Pollard, and Westmoreland Davis, and includes a list of campaign expenses (1922), and a printed copy of the "Inaugural Address of Governor Westmoreland Davis" (1918 Feb 1); and a report by Hon. E.P. Cox concerning railroads chartered in Virginia (1904).
Material related to Morven Park include files concerning the Sam Marcum lease; an appraisal; the boxwoods; an inventory; surveys and deed; soil conservation; and the Virginia State Department of Highways Right of Way.
Files pertaining to the accounts of Mrs. Davis include those of Henry G. Diefenbach and the United States Trust Company of New York. The financial affairs of her sisters are discussed in the files of Mrs. Jennie Inman Payne; the Estate of Willie Lee Inman and the United States Trust Company of New York account with Willie Lee Inman.
A good photograph of Governor Davis (1939) suitable for use in publications can be found in Box 6 and an electrostatic copy can also be found in the control folder for this collection.
Arrangement
The collection is in reverse chronological order within each folder, and is arranged in two series. Series I consists of correspondence and Series II consists of financial and legal papers, as well as a few miscellaneous personal folders.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence of Marguerite Davis and Paul Spivey 1955 May-1963, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Marguerite Davis and Paul Spivey 1942-1955 Apr, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of Westmoreland Davis and Paul Spivey re The Southern Planter1922-1942, n.d., 2 folders (Box 2)
- Financial & Legal Papers
  - Audits for Morven Farm & Loudoun Times Publishing Company, Inc. 1938-1940 (Box 3)
  - Carter, Ledyard & Milburn: re Estate of Marguerite Davis 1963-1966 (Box 3)
  - Central Manhattan Improvement Company 1912-1943 (Box 3)
  - Henry G. Diefenbach: U.S. Trust Company of New York 1956-1966, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Estate of Marguerite Davis 1962-1966, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Estate of Marguerite Davis: Deed of Trust 1954-1963 (Box 4)
  - Estate of Marguerite Davis: Florida Property 1963-1964 (Box 4)
  - Estate of Marguerite Davis: Will 1946 (Box 4)
  - Estate of Westmoreland Davis ca. 1942-1944, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Estate of Westmoreland Davis: Will 1935 (Box 4)
  - Estate of Willie Lee Inman 1896, 1915-1943, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Estate Tax Return of Marguerite Davis 1963 (Box 4)
  - Estate Tax Return of Westmoreland Davis 1942 (Box 4)
  - Federal Land Bank of Baltimore 1935-1943 (Box 5)
  - Federal Reserve Bank Directors 1914-1915 (Box 5)
  - Financial Summaries used for Tax Statements of Marguerite Davis 1941-1962, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Florida Trading Corporation 1941-1957 (Box 5)
  - Stirling Harrison: re Estate of Marguerite Davis 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - Hotel Chelsea, New York City 1883-1912, 1921-1942 (Box 5)
  - House Located at King & Cornwall Streets, Leesburg, Virginia 1962-1963 (Box 5)
  - Loudoun Times-Mirror 1943, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Sam L. Marcum: Morven Park Lease 1950, 1962-1963 (Box 6)
  - Market Commission Bill (Wisconsin) & Bureau of Markets Bill 1913 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous and Printed Material 1896-1967, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Morven Park Appraisal 1963-1964 (Box 6)
  - Morven Park: Boxwood Pest Control 1955 (Box 6)
  - Morven Park: Inventory 1926-1953 (Box 6)
  - Morven Park: Surveys and Deed 1935, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Morven Park Estate Survey Drawings 1932, n.d., 3 oversize sheets
  - Mrs. Jennie Inman Payne 1915-1919, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Photograph of Governor Westmoreland Davis 1939 (Box 6)
  - Political Papers of Westmoreland Davis 1917-1922, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Proxy Statements and Stock Certificates [1881?]-1897, 1945-1949 (Box 6)
  - Report of Honorable E.P. Cox to E.G. Leigh, Jr. of the Richmond Chamber of Commerce re "Charters of and Acts of Assembly relating to Roads Chartered in Virginia" 1904 (Box 6)
  - Soil Conservation Program - Morven Park Farm 1955-1956 (Box 6)
  - The Southern Planter Publishing Company 1942-1944 (Box 6)
  - [Sterling?] Silver Razor Strop belonging to Governor Davis n.d., artifact
  - United States Trust Company of New York 1935-1963 (Box 7)
  - United States Trust Company of New York: Statements of Account with Marguerite Davis 1934-1949, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - United States Trust Company of New York: Statements of Account with Willie Lee Inman 1943-1948 (Box 7)
  - Virginia State Department of Highways: Right of Way through Morven Park 1957-1958, 1963 (Box 7)
  - Warrenton Times Contest Contract 1915-1917 (Box 7)
  - Westmoreland Davis Memorial Foundation 1956-1966 (Box 7)